Finding Aid for Richard D. McLellan papers, 1978-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard D. McLellan papers 1978-2012
McLellan, Richard D.
2012060 Aa 2
Richard D. McLellan is a Michigan lawyer and government policy specialist. He has been actively engaged in government service and was an important advocate in Michigan’s school choice movement. The collection documents his work with TEACH Michigan, an organization established to amend Michigan’s constitution to allow use of school vouchers and increase the number of charter schools in the state. Also material related to speeches and remarks made on various subjects.
3.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Richard D. McLellan (donor no. 10744 ) in March 2012 and September 2013.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Richard D. McLellan was born in Paw Paw, Michigan. He graduated from Michigan State University in 1964 with a bachelor's degree in advertising. He earned his law degree from the University of Michigan Law School in 1967.
McLellan began his legal career as a lawyer in Fowlerville, Michigan where he also served as Chief Assistant Prosecuting Attorney for Livingston County, Michigan. In 1969 he joined the staff of Governor William G. Milliken where he served as an administrative assistant for policies and programs until 1973.
In 1973, McLellan launched a private law practice in Lansing, Michigan that grew into the lawyer firm of McLellan, Schlaybaugh and Whitbeck. The firm combined practices with Dykema, Gossett, Spencer, Goodnow & Trigg in 1982 where McLellan practiced until retiring in 2007. During his tenure at Dykema, McLellan served as head of the firm's Government Policy & Practice Group and as Managing Member of the firm's Lansing Office. He also served a term on the firm's Executive Committee.
In addition to his professional activities, McLellan has also accepted a variety of government service responsibilities: as both member and chair of the Michigan Law Revision Commission and as a member of the National Advisory Food and Drug Committee of the U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare.
McLellan was also involved in efforts to expand school choice for Michigan students. He drafted bipartisan legislation establishing charter schools as part of Michigan's system of free public schools. He also represented parties supporting the law after it was challenged by the Michigan Education Association and successfully argued in the Michigan Supreme Court the key decision upholding charter schools as constitutionally-established public schools.
The McLellan collection documents McLellan's work with TEACH Michigan, the organization established to support school choice measures in Michigan. These measures included a proposed amendment to Michigan's constitution to permit the use of school vouchers and to increase the number of charter schools operating in the state. The TEACH Michigan series has been arranged in the following subseries: Background, Charter Schools, Constitutional Amendment, Correspondence, Legislation, and Organizational Files.
Subjects:
McLellan, Richard D.; Dykema Gossett (Firm); Michigan Center for Charter Schools.; TEACH Michigan.; Charter schools--Michigan.; School choice--Michigan.
- TEACH Michigan
  The series documents McLellan's work with TEACH Michigan, the organization established to support school choice measures in Michigan. These measures included a proposed amendment to Michigan's constitution to permit the use of school vouchers and to increase the number of charter schools operating in the state. The TEACH Michigan series has been arranged in the following subseries: Background, Charter Schools, Constitutional Amendment, Correspondence, Legislation, and Organizational Files.
  - Background
    Background contains research relating to school choice and cases involving school voucher programs in other states.
    - "Better Schools through New Institutions" (Box 1)
    - Cases
      - Appellate Opinions Up for Review in 1993 (Box 1)
      - Attorney General Opinions (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Center for Workforce Preparation and Quality Education (Box 1)
    - Citizens Research Council 1978-1990 (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Constitutional Convention (Box 1)
    - Constitutional Provisions and Statues (Box 1)
    - Detroit Ballot Question (Box 1)
    - Heritage Foundation (Box 1)
    - Home Schools (Box 1)
    - Institute for Justice (Box 1)
    - John Coon (Box 1)
    - John Engler (Box 1)
    - Legislative Attempts 1990 (Box 1)
    - Mackinac Center, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Memos
      - General (Box 1)
      - Supreme Court (Box 1)
    - Michigan State Chamber of Commerce (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Journal Articles, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Other States
      - Alabama (Box 1)
      - California (Box 1)
      - Colorado (Box 1)
      - General (Box 1)
      - Illinois (Box 1)
      - Legislation (Box 1)
      - Minnesota (Box 1)
      - Oregon (Box 1)
      - Washington (Box 1)
      - Washington, DC (Box 1)
      - Wisconsin (Box 1)
    - "Parents, Teachers, and Children" (Box 1)
    - "Part of the Solution Rather Than Part of the Problem" (Box 1)
    - Religious Schools (Box 1)
    - Supreme Court (Box 1)
    - Surveys (Box 1)
    - Taxes (Box 1)
    - "Using Private Schools to Promote Public Values" (Box 1)
    - Vouchers (Box 1)
  - Charter Schools
    Charter Schools contains research related to charter school programs and information related to the institution of charter schools within Michigan.
    - Background (Box 1)
    - Cases (Box 1)
    - Compliance Procedures (Box 1)
    - Conferences (Box 2)
    - Contracts
      - Bylaws (Box 2)
      - Draft Charters (Box 2)
      - Huron State University and Metropolitan Charter School (Box 2)
      - Model Contract (Box 2)
      - Saginaw Valley State University 1994 (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2)
    - Governor's Office for Charter Schools (Box 2)
    - Legislation (Box 2)
    - Parochiaid (Box 2)
    - School Code (Box 2)
  - Constitutional Amendment
    The Constitutional Amendment subseries includes drafts of the proposed constitutional amendment, in addition to correspondence and memos relating to the drafting process.
    - Articles VII, IX, and XI (Box 2)
    - Article VIII Drafts, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Constitutionality 1978 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Language Alternatives (Box 2)
    - Memos (Box 2)
    - Outline of Amendments (Box 2)
    - Petition 1978 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    Correspondence includes mailings from the Michigan Department of Education, letters from officers of the Mackinac Center sent to RDM for his information, communications with Paul N. DeWeese, president of Michigan Citizens for Choice in Education (later renamed TEACH Michigan), and from George E. Ward, trustee of Saginaw Valley State University.
    - Department of Education (Box 2)
    - Mackinac Center (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - TEACH Michigan (Box 2)
    - Ward, George (Box 2)
  - Legislation
    Legislation includes copies of bills proposed in the Michigan House and Senate related to school choice. Also included are McLellan's communications with Michigan legislators about proposed legislation.
    - Bill Request 1994 (Box 2)
    - Enrolled House Bills (Box 2)
    - Enrolled Senate Bills (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2)
    - House and Senate Journals 1994 (Box 2)
    - House Bills (Box 2)
    - House Bill 5128 and substitutes (Box 2)
    - House Bill 5463 and substitutes (Box 2)
    - Senate Bills (Box 2)
    - Senate Bill 887 (Box 2)
    - Senate Joint Resolutions (Box 2)
  - Organizational Files
    The Organizational Files consist of communications with, and collected material from, organizations who were working for educational reform. These organizations include the Michigan Center for Charter Schools and TEACH Michigan. Many of these communications are with Paul N. DeWeese.
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Education Reform (Box 2)
    - Administration (Box 2)
    - Center for Public Justice 1990 (Box 2)
    - Citizens for More Sensible Financing of Education (Box 2)
    - Drafting Committee (Box 2)
    - Michigan Center for Charter Schools
      - General 1994 (Box 3)
      - Model Documents for Establishing a Charter Public School in Michigan 1994 (Box 3)
      - "Understanding Michigan's Charter School Law," 1994 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Citizens for Choice in Education 1990 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Citizens for Competitive Education Reform 1990 (Box 3)
    - TEACH Michigan
      - General (Box 3)
      - Meetings (Box 3)
      - Memos (Box 3)
      - Newsletters 1993-1994 (Box 3)
      - Proposed Revision to Michigan School Code (Box 3)
      - Reorganization (Box 3)
      - Strategic Plan (Box 3)
      - "TEACH Plan for Educational Reform in Michigan," 1991 (Box 3)
- Speeches, Remarks, Comments
  The series, Speeches Remarks, Comments, includes texts, talking points and outlines, correspondence, background information, meeting agenda, and material related to speeches and remarks made by McLellan on various subjects, between 1987 and 2012. Material in this series is organized chronologically and includes a donor-prepared item list with events' exact dates, places, and additional notes. Topics include domestic and international trade and business, politics, government, education, ethics, institutional change, among others.
  - Item index (Box 3)
  - 1987
    - Directors and Officers Liability and Indemnification (Box 3)
    - Law Enforcement Appreciation Night (Box 3)
    - Governor Engler/McLellan speech (Box 3)
    - Trends in Association Law (Box 3)
    - Legal Implications-New (Box 3)
  - 1988
    - Employment Contracts for Chamber of Commerce Executives (Box 3)
    - Role of Politics and Lobbying in the Practice if Administrative Law (Box 3)
    - Point/Counterpoint: the Free Market vs. Social Engineering through Insurance Regulation (Box 3)
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 3)
    - People, Power, Politics (Box 3)
  - 1989
    - Legal Update to Trade Associations (Box 3)
    - "Globalization" Take Heart! (Box 3)
      (program)
    - Enhancing Technology Business Development through Public Policy Decision Making (Box 3)
    - U.S.-Canada Free Trade Agreement, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - International Trade Opportunities Briefing (Box 3)
    - Legal Rights of Volunteers: Who Advocates? (Box 3)
    - Role of Law in a Market Driven System and in the World Economy (Box 3)
    - Benefits Your Community Can Get from the Free Trade Agreement-If You are Ready (Box 3)
  - 1990
    - Avoiding the Pitfalls of Starting and Operating Business (Box 3)
    - Highlights of Proposed Revised APA (Box 3)
    - Doing Business in Asia (Box 3)
    - Austin v. Chamber of Commerce Means to Business and Trade Associates, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Computer Software Tax (Box 3)
    - Emerging Market Economies in Eastern Europe (Box 3)
    - Update on the State Government Transition Process (Box 3)
  - 1991
    - World of "Magic" Allen (Box 3)
    - Gubernatorial Transition, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - WJR-AM radio interview with J. P. McCarthy (Box 3)
      (confirmation letter)
    - Gus Harrison Facility Dedication (Box 3)
    - Understanding Long Term Care Financing in the 90's (Box 3)
    - Future of Education in Michigan (Box 3)
    - Give them a Hand Award (Box 3)
  - 1992
    - Primer on Campaign Finance (Box 3)
  - 1993
    - Ethics in Government (Box 3)
    - North American Free Trade Agreement (Box 3)
    - Governor's Authority to Reorganize the DNR (Box 3)
    - Overview of Film and Television Packaging, Production, Marketing/Distribution and Networking (Box 3)
  - 1994
    - Michigan Forward Magazine, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (thank you letter)
    - Why Hate Hamlet? (Box 3)
    - NAFTA and Its Impact (Box 3)
    - Leveling the Playing Field (Box 3)
      (article)
    - Trade and Professional Associations (Box 3)
    - What is a Charter School? (Box 3)
    - "Golden Apple" Presentation to Joseph Antonini (Box 3)
  - 1995
    - Charter Schools, Public Schools (Box 3)
    - How the Bingo Act Will Impact PAC Fundraising (Box 3)
  - 1996
    - Seminar devoted to public policy (Box 3)
  - 1997
    - Lobbying (Box 4)
  - 1998
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 4)
  - 1999
    - Trip to Nigeria (Box 4)
    - Legislation Impacting Indian Country (Box 4)
    - Founding Principles of this Fraternity (Box 4)
    - Educational Choice: Charter Schools and Vouchers (Box 4)
  - 2000
    - Federal-State-Tribal Relations (Box 4)
    - Let Local Votes Count (Box 4)
    - Constitutional and Legal Ramifications of Ballot Proposal I (Box 4)
    - Elements of Successful Advocacy and Lobbying in the U.S. (Box 4)
  - 2001
    - Inaugural (Box 4)
    - How to Affect Real Campaign Reform without Hurting Republicans (Box 4)
    - Michigan's Voucher Proposal and the Future of School Choice (Box 4)
    - Moldovan Study Tour Group (Box 4)
    - Michigan Voucher Proposal Would Pass a Constitutional Challenge (Box 4)
    - Voucher Debate (Box 4)
  - 2002
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 4)
  - 2003
    - Opposition to HB4764-Legislative Intervention in Pending Litigation (Box 4)
    - Legal Analyses and Observations (Affirmative Action) (Box 4)
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 4)
    - Ethics and Compliance Issues for House Republicans (Box 4)
    - International Visitor Program (Box 4)
  - 2004
    - Health Care Iraq (Box 4)
    - Tribal Constitutional issues in the Self Determination Era (Box 4)
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 4)
    - Ethics Laws for Public Office Holders (Box 4)
  - 2005
    - Policy Implications of Competing Telcom Technologies (Box 4)
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 4)
  - 2006
    - "Snap Shot" of Existing Economic Development Laws (Box 4)
  - 2007
    - Speech by Cardinal Maida (Box 4)
      (comments)
  - 2008
    - Ingham County GOP Convention (Box 4)
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 4)
  - 2009
    - Ethics and Compliance Issues (Box 4)
    - Constitution as a Basis for Government (Box 4)
    - Ethics and "Institutional Corruption" Matters (Box 4)
    - Michigan Excellence in Public Service (Box 4)
      (graduation ceremony)
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 4)
    - Michigan State University College of Law (Box 4)
  - 2010
    - Citizens United Symposium (Box 4)
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 4)
  - 2011
    - Celebrating a Leadership Legacy of Excellence (Box 4)
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 4)
  - 2012
    - Elected Officials and "Ordinary and Necessary Business Expenses" (Box 4)
    - Voucher Discussion (Box 4)
    - "Michigan-Canada" Bridge and the Moroun Anti-Bridge Proposed Constitutional Amendment (Box 4)
    - Understanding Institutional Change (Box 4)
  - Undated material (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
Related Material
The Bentley Library also houses the records of TEACH Michigan.